A Guide to the Papers of the Noel Family,
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the Noel Family
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
13371
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The collection was given to the Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library at the University of Virginia by Edgar Estes Noel of 20 Marina Dr., Newport News, Va. 23608-3117 on July 21, 2005.
Biographical/Historical Information
Edgar Estes Noel II was born in Huntington, West Virginia in 1933 to Dr. William Edgar Noel and Lelia Ophelia Wash Noel. They lived in Huntington, West Virginia and then moved to Denbigh, (Newport News) Virginia where Dr. Noel continued his practice as a physician and foot specialist. In later years, Lelia Noel suffered from diabetes as well as asthma, and needed constant care. Dr. Noel treated patients until his death from a heart attack in 1980. Lelia died seven months after him. They were both avid readers and antique collectors and passed these interests on to Edgar.
Edgar attended Phillips Exeter preparatory school and graduated from the University of Virginia in 1954 with a B.S. degree in Education. Following his service in the R.O.T. C. at the University of Virginia, he entered the United States Army Counter Intelligence Corps and served as a Second Lieutenant for four years. As part of his training, he attended Army Language School in Monterey, California (1955) where he studied Japanese for forty-six weeks. He was assigned security detail on Four Star General Lyman Louis Lemnitzer, Commander in Chief of the United Nations, and later with Four Star Generals Isaac D. White, and George W. Decker of the Eighth United States Army in Tokyo, Japan (1956-1957 Camp Zama.)
From 1958 to 1960, after a trip to Europe, he returned to the University of Virginia and received a Masters degree in history. His thesis was on the first Americans in Japan. He also wrote poetry and had several poems published throughout his career. He married Ida Jeanne Thompson in 1959 and she worked as a receptionist at the University of the Virginia Graduate School of Business while Edgar finished school (and worked a part time job in the Reserve room in Alderman Library under the supervision of [Mrs.] Irving). In 1960 Edgar received his first assignment in the United States Information Office in Bangkok, Thailand where their first son, William E. Noel II (Wen) is born.
From 1961 to 1963 Edgar was stationed in Kwangju, Korea with his wife and son. After a visit to Virginia in 1963, their second child, Laura Forsyth Noel, was born in Korea. In 1964 he was assigned to Yokohama, Japan to study more Japanese and their third child, Norbourn William Noel "Bruz" was born. From 1965 to 1971, he worked as the Director of the Fukuoka American Cultural Center in Japan.
In 1972 he accepted the position of Material Development Officer for the Intelligence Agency's Teaching Division in Georgetown, Guyana until 1974 when he was promoted to Deputy Public Affairs Officer in Lagos, Nigeria. In 1979 Edgar was stationed in Bombay, India and was promoted to U.S. Senior Foreign Service Officer in 1981. He retired from Foreign Service in 1984 and moved to their family home in Denbigh, (Newport News) Virginia.
Between 1978 and 1979 the Noel's three children went to boarding schools (and college) in the United States because there was not a high school equivalent in Nigeria. William Noel "Wen" attended Fork Union Military Academy and Virginia Military Institute. Laura Noel attended Staunton Hall School for Girls and Randolph Macon Woman's College, and Norbourn Noel "Bruz" attended Woodberry Forest School and the University of Georgia.
Each member of the Noel families' distinct personalities comes across in their letters. William Noel, as the older brother, is very responsible and dedicated to his plans for a military career. He becomes a Lieutenant Colonel in the Armed Services. Laura Noel is witty, and outgoing. She excels in theatre and stars as the lead role in plays at school (as did her parents). After receiving a B.S. degree in Education from Randolph Macon Woman's College, she worked as a historical interpreter in Colonial Williamsburg and attended classes at the College of William and Mary. Norbourn Noel "Bruz" studied to become a landscape architect and settled in Fort Lauderdale, Florida. His letters are frequently accompanied with his own amusing cartoon illustrations of his daily life. He is a talented artist who has a great sense of humor and also cares deeply about everything that is natural and honest. Edgar worked hard, encouraged his children with their studies, supported their individual interests, and frequently suffered from ulcers due to concerns about his work. Jeanne kept the family afloat with her sense of humor, affectionate nature, and devoted attention to Edgar's affairs. The three children and their parents were close and wrote about their relationships, and the events in their daily lives.
There are also letters from Edgar's older sister, Melissa Catherine Adkins Norman who had two marriages and a son from her first marriage, Lee Adkins. Melissa's first husband, Bill Ed Adkins had failing health which caused him an early death. Melissa's second husband did not have any income and after a year of marriage, the Noels discover that she was hospitalized in West Virginia. She moved back to Newport News, studied shorthand, and worked as a manager in retail businesses. After Edgar retired from Foreign Service, she returned to West Virginia to live by herself. Her son, Lee, married and had two children, Mathew, and Lesley.
Edgar's maternal grandparents were Melissa Catherine Jones Wash and Cyreneous O. Wash. His paternal grandparents were Dr. Edgar Estes Noel and Minnie George Noel. There is correspondence to Edgar from both sets of grandparents. There are also letters from Dr. William E. Noel's sister, Mary Virginia Noel Evans. She was married to Brown Evans, and they lived in Washington, D. C. They had two children, a son Andy Brown Evans (also nicknamed Bruz), who had Down Syndrome, and a daughter, Bidley Evans.
Edgar's wife, Jeanne was the only child of LeRoy (Roy) S. and Jeanette Thompson who lived in Richmond, Virginia and then retired in Fort Myers, Florida. LeRoy Thompson was an expert in stocks and financial planning. Robert and Vi Forsythe, brother and sister-in-law of Jeanette Thompson moved with them to Florida, and they enjoyed retirement together, frequently going out to dinner and playing cards.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of the personal and family correspondence of Edgar Estes Noel II from 1952 to 1992. Mr. Noel worked for the Army Counter Intelligence Corps as a Japanese language specialist and the U. S. Information Agency as a Deputy Public Affairs Officer, and Senior Foreign Service Information Officer. The family correspondence begins when Noel was a student at the University of Virginia and continues throughout his career in Bangkok, Thailand; Kwangju, Korea; Tokyo, Japan; Georgetown, Guyana; Lagos, Nigeria; and Bombay, India. It consists of ca. 3,698 items, 3 linear feet in 7 Hollinger boxes.
The collection primarily consists of family letters that describe the personal history of the Noels including some information on the schools that the Noels attended. The school information includes event calendars, football program guides, or comments about a particular school, and is included with the correspondence. The schools mentioned are the University of Virginia, Randolph Macon Woman's College, Virginia Military Institute, University of Georgia, Staunton Hall School for Girls, Woodberry Forest School, and Fork Union Military Academy. There is significant information about the University of Virginia when Edgar was an undergraduate student and writes a column for The Cavalier Daily from 1952 to 1955 and later when he is a graduate student in 1958.
Articles and news clippings mentioning important world political events and figures are enclosed with the family letters. The letters from Edgar Noel to his family reveal his passion for learning about other cultures and his commitment to teaching principles of democracy to underdeveloped countries. By 1962 when Noel was stationed in Korea he wrote about his frustration with foreign governments that, he said, blamed the American government and requested American assistance without taking any responsibility for their own situations.
Some of the important world events and individuals mentioned in the correspondence are: the 1960 Civil War in Laos; the 1962 Korean situation with President Park Chung-hee; the visit of Mrs. Jean Kennedy Smith (1961); the visit of Vice President Lyndon Johnson and Lady Bird Johnson (1962); the 1963 Korean Presidential Election; the death of President John F. Kennedy (1963); the 1964 student demonstrations in Korea; Congressman Thomas N. Downing's amendment to bring prayer into schools; the death of President Harry S. Truman in 1973; Watergate and the resignation of Richard S. Nixon in 1974; Nigeria's high production of oil (1975); an attempted coup in Nigeria (1975); the Presidential debates of Jimmy Carter in 1976; Iranian hostage situation and Iranian demonstrations (1979 November); Russian attack on Afghanistan (1980 January-March); visit of Muhammad Ali in Bombay, India in 1980; and Noel's criticism of Nelson Mandela (1988).
Correspondents include friends and business associates: Norman L.Dobyns; Tweetsie Parker; Letcher H. Reid; Mrs. Pynn J. Finch; Bert Edward McCormick; Ron and Bess Dietrich; Kwangju Christian Hospital; Thomas N. Downing; Byron and Lucille Hess; Nancy Niklos; Harriet Crawford Jones; Mabel Wing Jones; and Suetaka Hatanaka, President of Minaminihon Broadcasting Co. There are also letters from Senator Harry F. Byrd, Jr., Senator John Warner, and Senator Paul Trible about references for Noel's son, William Edgar Noel "Wen," who was applying to the United States Military Academy at West Point.
There is also correspondence from Edgar's paternal great-grandmother, Mary Hinchman George from 1856 to 1864 which includes letters written during the Civil War. She wrote a letter to her parents on November 19, 1860 about the [presidential] election. In another letter dated April 20, 1861 she mentioned the Battle of Fort Sumter, the capture of Major [Robert] Anderson, and the indecision of some Virginians (now West Virginians) about their loyalties to the Unionists or Secessionists. There is also a letter dated October 21, 1861 describing the death of her brother, William Hinchmen, from typhoid fever. There is a letter dated January 1862 from her sister, Mollie Poage, about the overwhelming number of burnings, robberies, and murders between Unionists and Secessionists in West Virginia. The letter mentions that Colonel Jackson [General Thomas Stonewall Jackson] and General [Joseph] Johnston are searching for the murderers.
There is more correspondence from Edgar's maternal great-grandfather, Alexander Jones, from 1861 and 1863 concerning the Civil War. A letter dated August 17, 1861 from Henry L. Bell (unknown relative) to Catherine [Jones] describes the battle of Phillipi [sic] and the battle of Rich Mountain where Brigadier General Robert Garnett is killed. The second letter, dated February 23, 1863 has advice to Henry T. Bell from his sister about camp life. Some of the letters are accompanied with typed transcriptions.
There are also letters from 1878 to 1888 from Edgar Noel's great-uncle, D. T. Jones to his brother, Alexander Jones, and to D. T. Jones' niece. There is also a letter dated March 30, 1883 from a girlfriend of Edgar's grandfather, Edgar Estes Noel I.
Arrangement
The letters are arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- Correspondence of the Noel Family
  - Civil War Letters, 1856-1864, 19 letters of correspondence from Mary Hinchmen George and 2 letters of correspondence from Henry L. Bell, an unknown relative of Alexander Jones. (Box-folder 1:1)
    There is a letter dated November 19, 1860 from Mary Hinchmen George to her parents about the consequences of the Republican Party winning the 1860 [presidential] election, and another letter dated April 20, 1861 from her to her parents about the battle of Fort Sumter; taking Major [Robert] Anderson prisoner; and the decision of Virginians to support either the Unionists or the Secessionists.
    There is also a letter dated October 21, 1861 in which Mary Hinchman describes the death of her brother, William Hinchmen, from typhoid fever, and a letter dated January 1862 from Mary's sister, Mollie Poage about murders being committed against Unionists supporters. The letter mentions that Stonewall Jackson and General Joseph Johnston would like to find the men who are committing these murders.
    There is a letter dated October 23, 1861 from [a cousin, J. A. Symms] to [Mary Hinchmen] about marching in the rain, day and night from Saltville, Virginia to Bristol, Tennessee. There is also a letter dated December 5, 1864 from family members about General [William Tecumseh] Sherman and "Old Bobbie Lee" that mentions the Georgia Expedition.
    There are 2 letters of correspondence from Henry L. Bell, one to Catherine [Wash Jones] Edgar's great-grandmother (Lelia's grandmother), about the Battle of Phillipi [sic], the battle of Rich Mountain, and the death of Brigadier General Robert Garnett dated August 17, 1861. There is also a letter dated February 23, 1863 from the sister of Henry L. Bell giving him advice regarding the sinful temptations of camp life.
  - Family Letters, 1878-1888 (Box-folder 1:2)
    Correspondence of Mary Hinchmen George and correspondence from D. T. Jones to Alexander Jones; a letter from John W. [Ellis] and a letter from a girlfriend of Edgar Estes Noel.
  - Correspondence to Edgar Estes Noel I from Mary Robert Webb Noel and to other family members, 1895-1922, 8 letters. (Box-folder 1:3)
    There is a letter from Mary Robert Webb Noel (Edgar's great-grandmother) to her son Edgar Estes Noel I, (Edgar's grandfather). There is also a letter dated December 24, 1900 from Thomas George (brother of Mary Robert Webb Noel) to his niece; and a letter dated May 2, 1904 from Mary George (great-maternal grandmother of Edgar Estes Noel II) to her niece. There is another letter dated September 28, 1922 from John L. George (great-uncle of Edgar Estes Noel II) to his niece, Mary Noel Evans.
  - Parents of Edgar Estes Noel II, 1925-1945, 28 letters. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Letters from William Edgar Noel (father of Edgar Estes Noel II) to his future wife and mother of Edgar, Lelia Ophelia Wash Noel; letters to William E. Noel and Lelia Ophelia Wash Noel from their parents; letters from Lelia's brother Cy during World War II about how he misses his wife Jamie and the family; an invitation for six-day old Edgar Estes Noel II to his sister, Melissa's, birthday party.
  - University of Virginia, 1946-1952, 56 letters. (Box-folder 1:5)
    Letters from Dr. William E. Noel to his sister, Mary Virginia Noel Evans; notes on a trip to New York City by Mary Virginia Noel Evans; letter of acceptance from Phillips Exeter Academy for Edgar Noel; letters from Edgar to his parents while he attended the University of Virginia, some with the letterheads of the University of Virginia or Sigma Chi. There is a program of the Sweetheart Banquet of Sigma Chi.
  - University of Virginia and R.O.T.C., 1953, 52 items. (Box-folder 1:6)
    Letters from Edgar at the University of Virginia and R.O.T.C. Summer Camp at Fort Eustis to his parents regarding his academics, social life and finances (his new car); his articles in The Cavalier Daily which include his opinions about President Darden, fraternities, and drinking at the University; letters to Edgar from his mother, Lelia Noel, about family news and travels.
  - Sigma Chi Meeting Notes, 1954-1955, 1 item. (Box-folder 1:7)
    A large collection of annotated notes from Sigma Chi meetings after Edgar's graduation that mentions many of his friends and peers.
  - Norman L. Dobyns; Army Service in Baltimore, Maryland, 1954, 50 items. (Box-folder 1:8)
    Fort Holabird, Baltimore, Maryland. Letters between Edgar and his parents including a discussion of a possible marriage proposal which does not pan out; letters from Edgar's best friend, Norman L. Dobyns "Dob." Edgar made Dean's List and writes about an "A" that he received in English from his professor, Arthur Kyle Davis which he describes as a high honor.
  - Army Language School, 1955, 71 items. (Box-folder 1:9)
    Letters between Edgar and his parents, discussing his sister's loss of her pregnancy, his parent's new house, and his trip to Monterey, California where he attended Army Language School to study Japanese; Edgar writes that army life broadens the mind and he says that he and his classmates are "fed up with the narrow mindedness of their state toward segregation."
    There are also letters from his maternal grandfather, Cyreneous O. Wash and his friend, Norman Dobyns.
  - Arrival in Japan, 1956, 92 items. (Box-folder 1:10)
    Letters from Edgar to his parents describing his trip to Tokyo via Hawaii, and his first impressions of Tokyo. He was assigned security detail on Four Star Generals Lyman Louis Leminzer and Isaac D. White who were in the United Nations Command, and the Eighth U. S. Army. He writes about the devastation from World War I fire bombings, the luxurious treatment of American soldiers overseas by the U.S. Government, and the election news of Eisenhower defeating Adlai Stevenson. He also made a comparison of the Russian Government to Adolph Hitler. He mentions that he received the latest news on the Hungarian Revolution. He also writes about the Japanese strike against the United States for tightening its employee restrictions. Edgar writes that the Japanese have no right to complain since they lost the war.
    There are also letters from Edgar's best friend, Norman L. Dobyns, who was serving in the Department of the Army, and a thank you letter from Edgar to Dobyn's girlfriend, Tweetsie Parker. In addition there is correspondence from Edgar to his future wife, Ida Jeanne Thompson, the roommate of Tweetsie Parker.
  - Camp Zama, Japan, 1957, 85 items. (Box-folder 1:11)
    Letters between Edgar and his parents about his security detail for Four Star Generals Isaac D.White and George H.Decker. Much of his time was spent sight-seeing or escorting the wives of the Generals and their friends to antique shops and restaurants. He saw a film on World War II from the Japanese perspective and was impressed at the massive bombing (855 bombers per day) and the power of the United States. He also mentions that the Japanese think that the warm weather was a result of the Atom Bomb tests, but he writes of his skepticism. Edgar disparages the Japanese worshop of [Nobesuki] Kishi.
    Other correspondence includes a letter to Edgar from his grandmother [Mamma] about the death of his grandfather, Cyreneous O. Wash; letters from Ida Jeanne Thompson to her parents [Leroy S. and Jeanette Thompson] from her trip abroad in France and Italy.
  - End of tour of duty in Japan; Trip to Europe; Graduate School at the University of Virginia, 1958, 42 items. (Box-folder 2:1)
    Letters between Edgar and his parents and to Jeanne Thompson about his travels, wanting to see Jeanne, his job in Alderman Library; and winning 1st place in an All Japanese Fine Arts Show. He also writes about the student riots at the University; the closing of the Charlottesville Schools; the students' dislike of UVA President Colgate Darden; his studies; and the good impressions he has made upon University of Virginia Professor Edward Younger.
  - June-July Travel letters Europe, 1958, 39 items. (Box-folder 2:2)
  - Travel letters Europe, 1958 August, 14 items. (Box-folder 2:3)
  - UVA; Edgar Noel and Jeanne Thompson, 1959, 60 items. (Box-folder 2:4)
    Letters to his parents and Jeanne about their engagement; letters to his parents about his heavy work load at the University; his thesis on Americans in Japan; his job in Alderman Library; and the popularity of the University of Virginia President, Edgar F. Shannon.
    Other correspondence includes a letter from his grandmother [Mamma]; his friend Bert McCormick, (at Oxford) congratulating Edgar and Jeanne on their engagement; other congratulatory letters on their engagement; a photocopy of a news clipping announcing their engagement; an invitation from their wedding; and a honeymoon schedule.
  - Bangkok, Thailand, 1960, 24 items. (Box-folder 2:5)
    Letters from Edgar to his parents about graduation; an invitation to Bert Edward McCormick's graduation ceremony from Oxford; a letter from McCormick to Edgar's parents about Berts' plans for traveling; Edgar's new job with the United States Intelligence Agency in Bangkok, Thailand; traveling to Bangkok; Jeanne's pregnancy; and the civil war in Laos.
  - Kwangju, Korea, 1961, 74 items. (Box-folder 2:6)
    Letters from Edgar and Jeanne to their parents about having Charlie Jankins, a two time gold medalist in track from the 1956 Olympics, over for dinner and their first impressions of Korea. Edgar writes about being able to use propaganda against Russia since he was a press writer and an article is enclosed in which he writes about the Russians being a world threat. There is also information on the civil war in Laos; the opening ceremony of the New Friendship Highway that the United States built in Thailand; a 14 nationconference in Geneva; and a visit of the Vice President of the United States, Lyndon Johnson, Lady Bird Johnson, and John F. Kennedy's sister, [Mrs. Jean Kennedy Smith].
    There is a telegram announcing the birth of their son, William E. Noel II "Wen;" a letter from Edgar and his family to his cousin, Andrew Brown Evans who has Down Syndrome and is the son of Mary Virginia Noel Evans. There are printed materials including a copy of the Fortnightly paper, published by USIS in Bangkok; an article written by Edgar Noel for the international USIA file about the visit of Ladybird Johnson; USIA Correspondent newsletter vol. 3, no. 6 June-July 1961 with an article about Edgar going on a bamboo raft traveling down the Ping River.
  - Kwangju, Korea, 1962-1963, 61 items. (Box-folder 2:7)
    Letters from Edgar to his parents about Korean food and customs; a political situation in which the Korean Military Government (Park Chung Hee) wants to remain in power and the civilian government wants to take over. Edgar writes about his own frustration with the corruption in the Korean government and wishes that they would stop blaming America while simultaneously asking for American aid. Other events that he mentionsare a cholera epidemic in Korea; floods in Sun Cho; and the death of President John F. Kennedy.
    Other correspondence includes a telegram announcing the birth of Edgar and Jeanne's second child, Laura Forsyth. There is also a letter from Bess Dietrich, and letters from family members including Jeanne's grandmother, J. G. Steiner. Edgar asks his father to leave a greater portion of the Noel estate to his sister, Melissa. Edgar, Jeanne and the children visit their parents in their new home in Newport News, Virginia. There are also photographs of Wen, Laura, and their friend Sarah Dietrich. There are printed materials including news clippings about Edgar's talk at the Northampton Lions Club meeting; and an article about Mrs. Ah-ra Cho, executive director of the Kwangju YWCA, who visited Edgar's parents in Newport News,Virginia. There is also a church service program for Emmanuel Church in Richmond, Va. that welcomes Wen and Laura as new members.
  - Kwangju, Korea; Yokohama, Japan, 1964, 59 items. (Box-folder 2:8)